<refentry id="repmgr-standby-register" xreflabel="repmgr standby register">
  <indexterm>
    <primary>repmgr standby register</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>repmgr standby register</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>repmgr standby register</refname>
    <refpurpose>add a standby's information to the &repmgr; metadata</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
      <command>repmgr standby register</command> adds a standby's information to
      the &repmgr; metadata. This command needs to be executed to enable
      promote/follow operations and to allow &repmgrd; to work with the node.
      An existing standby can be registered using this command. Execute with the
      <literal>--dry-run</literal> option to check what would happen without actually registering the
      standby.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        If providing the configuration file location with <literal>-f/--config-file</literal>,
        avoid using a relative path, as &repmgr; stores the configuration file location
        in the repmgr metadata for use when &repmgr; is executed remotely (e.g. during
        <xref linkend="repmgr-standby-switchover"/>). &repmgr; will attempt to convert the
          a relative path into an absolute one, but this may not be the same as the path you
          would explicitly provide (e.g. <filename>./repmgr.conf</filename> might be converted
          to <filename>/path/to/./repmgr.conf</filename>, whereas you'd normally write
          <filename>/path/to/repmgr.conf</filename>).
      </para>
    </note>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="repmgr-standby-register-wait-start" xreflabel="repmgr standby register --wait-start">
   <title>Waiting for the the standby to start</title>
   <para>
     By default, &repmgr; will wait 30 seconds for the standby to become available before
     aborting with a connection error. This is useful when setting up a standby from a script,
     as the standby may not have fully started up by the time <command>repmgr standby register</command>
     is executed.
   </para>
   <para>
     To change the timeout, pass the desired value with the <literal>--wait-start</literal> option.
     A value of <literal>0</literal> will disable the timeout.
   </para>
   <para>
     The timeout will be ignored if <literal>-F/--force</literal> was provided.
   </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="repmgr-standby-register-wait-sync" xreflabel="repmgr standby register --wait-sync">
   <title>Waiting for the registration to propagate to the standby</title>
   <para>
     Depending on your environment and workload, it may take some time for the standby's node record
     to propagate from the primary to the standby. Some actions (such as starting
     &repmgrd;) require that the standby's node record
     is present and up-to-date to function correctly.
   </para>
   <para>
    By providing the option <option>--wait-sync</option> to the
    <command>repmgr standby register</command> command, &repmgr; will wait
    until the record is synchronised before exiting. An optional timeout (in
    seconds) can be added to this option (e.g. <option>--wait-sync=60</option>).
   </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="repmgr-standby-register-inactive-node" xreflabel="Registering an inactive node">
   <title>Registering an inactive node</title>
   <para>
    Under some circumstances you may wish to register a standby which is not
    yet running; this can be the case when using provisioning tools to create
    a complex replication cluster, or if the node was not cloned by &repmgr;.
   </para>
   <para>
    In this case, by using the <option>-F/--force</option>
    option and providing the connection parameters to the primary server,
    the standby can be registered even if it has not yet been started.
   </para>
   <tip>
     <para>
       Connection parameters can either be provided either as a <literal>conninfo</literal> string
       (e.g. <option>-d 'host=node1 user=repmgr'</option> or as individual connection parameters
        (<option>-h/--host</option>, <option>-d/--dbname</option>,
       <option>-U/--user</option>, <option>-p/--port</option> etc.).
     </para>
   </tip>

   <para>
    Similarly, with cascading replication it may be necessary to register
    a standby whose upstream node has not yet been registered - in this case,
    using <option>-F/--force</option> will result in the creation of an inactive placeholder
    record for the upstream node, which will however later need to be registered
    with the <option>-F/--force</option> option too.
   </para>
   <para>
    When used with <command>repmgr standby register</command>, care should be taken that use of the
    <option>-F/--force</option> option does not result in an incorrectly configured cluster.
   </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="repmgr-standby-register-node-cloned-other-source">
    <title>Registering a node not cloned by repmgr</title>
    <para>
      If you've cloned a standby using another method (e.g. <application>barman</application>'s
     <command><ulink url="https://docs.pgbarman.org/#recover">barman recover</ulink></command>
     command), register the node as detailed in section
     <xref linkend="repmgr-standby-register-inactive-node"/> then execute
     <link linkend="repmgr-standby-create-recovery-conf">repmgr standby clone --replication-conf-only</link>
     to generate the appropriate replication configuration.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>

    <title>Options</title>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>--dry-run</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Check prerequisites but don't actually register the standby.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry>
       <term><option>-F</option>/<option>--force</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Overwrite an existing node record
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>--upstream-node-id</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            ID of the upstream node to replicate from (optional)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>--wait-start</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            wait for the standby to start (timeout in seconds, default 30 seconds)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry>
        <term><option>--wait-sync</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            wait for the node record to synchronise to the standby (optional timeout in seconds)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>


    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="repmgr-standby-register-events">
    <title>Event notifications</title>
    <para>
      A <literal>standby_register</literal> <link linkend="event-notifications">event notification</link>
      will be generated immediately after the node record is updated on the primary.
    </para>

    <para>
      If the <option>--wait-sync</option> option is provided, a <literal>standby_register_sync</literal>
      event notification  will be generated immediately after the node record has synchronised to the
      standby.
    </para>

    <para>
      If provided, &repmgr; will substitute the placeholders <literal>%p</literal> with the node ID of the
      primary node, <literal>%c</literal> with its <literal>conninfo</literal> string, and
      <literal>%a</literal> with its node name.
    </para>

  </refsect1>

</refentry>
