<chapter id="repmgrd-automatic-failover" xreflabel="Automatic failover with repmgrd">

 <title>Automatic failover with repmgrd</title>

 <indexterm>
   <primary>repmgrd</primary>
   <secondary>automatic failover</secondary>
 </indexterm>

 <para>
  &repmgrd; is a management and monitoring daemon which runs
  on each node in a replication cluster. It can automate actions such as
  failover and updating standbys to follow the new primary, as well as
  providing monitoring information about the state of each standby.
 </para>

 <sect1 id="repmgrd-witness-server" xreflabel="Using a witness server with repmgrd">
   <title>Using a witness server</title>

 <indexterm>
   <primary>repmgrd</primary>
   <secondary>witness server</secondary>
 </indexterm>

 <indexterm>
   <primary>witness server</primary>
   <secondary>repmgrd</secondary>
 </indexterm>

 <para>
   A <xref linkend="witness-server"/> is a normal PostgreSQL instance which
   is not part of the streaming replication cluster; its purpose is, if a
   failover situation occurs, to provide proof that it is the primary server
   itself which is unavailable, rather than e.g. a network split between
   different physical locations.
 </para>

 <para>
   A typical use case for a witness server is a two-node streaming replication
   setup, where the primary and standby are in different locations (data centres).
   By creating a witness server in the same location (data centre) as the primary,
   if the primary becomes unavailable it's possible for the standby to decide whether
   it can promote itself without risking a "split brain" scenario: if it can't see either the
   witness or the primary server, it's likely there's a network-level interruption
   and it should not promote itself. If it can see the witness but not the primary,
   this proves there is no network interruption and the primary itself is unavailable,
   and it can therefore promote itself (and ideally take action to fence the
   former primary).
 </para>
 <note>
   <para>
     <emphasis>Never</emphasis> install a witness server on the same physical host
     as another node in the replication cluster managed by &repmgr; - it's essential
     the witness is not affected in any way by failure of another node.
   </para>
 </note>
 <para>
   For more complex replication scenarios, e.g. with multiple datacentres, it may
   be preferable to use location-based failover, which ensures that only nodes
   in the same location as the primary will ever be promotion candidates;
   see <xref linkend="repmgrd-network-split"/> for more details.
 </para>

 <note>
   <simpara>
     A witness server will only be useful if &repmgrd;
     is in use.
   </simpara>
 </note>

 <sect2 id="creating-witness-server">
   <title>Creating a witness server</title>
 <para>
   To create a witness server, set up a normal PostgreSQL instance on a server
   in the same physical location as the cluster's primary server.
 </para>
 <para>
   This instance should <emphasis>not</emphasis> be on the same physical host as the primary server,
   as otherwise if the primary server fails due to hardware issues, the witness
   server will be lost too.
 </para>
 <note>
   <simpara>
     &repmgr; 3.3 and earlier provided a <command>repmgr create witness</command>
     command, which would automatically create a PostgreSQL instance. However
     this often resulted in an unsatisfactory, hard-to-customise instance.
   </simpara>
 </note>
 <para>
   The witness server should be configured in the same way as a normal
   &repmgr; node; see section <xref linkend="configuration"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
   Register the witness server with <xref linkend="repmgr-witness-register"/>.
   This will create the &repmgr; extension on the witness server, and make
   a copy of the &repmgr; metadata.
 </para>
 <note>
   <simpara>
    As the witness server is not part of the replication cluster, further
    changes to the &repmgr; metadata will be synchronised by
    &repmgrd;.
   </simpara>
 </note>
 <para>
   Once the witness server has been configured, &repmgrd;
   should be started.
 </para>

 <para>
  To unregister a witness server, use <xref linkend="repmgr-witness-unregister"/>.
 </para>

 </sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="repmgrd-network-split" xreflabel="Handling network splits with repmgrd">
 <title>Handling network splits with repmgrd</title>
 <indexterm>
   <primary>repmgrd</primary>
   <secondary>network splits</secondary>
 </indexterm>

 <indexterm>
   <primary>network splits</primary>
 </indexterm>

 <para>
  A common pattern for replication cluster setups is to spread servers over
  more than one datacentre. This can provide benefits such as geographically-
  distributed read replicas and DR (disaster recovery capability). However
  this also means there is a risk of disconnection at network level between
  datacentre locations, which would result in a split-brain scenario if
  servers in a secondary data centre were no longer able to see the primary
  in the main data centre and promoted a standby among themselves.
 </para>
 <para>
  &repmgr; enables provision of &quot;<xref linkend="witness-server"/>&quot; to
  artificially create a quorum of servers in a particular location, ensuring
  that nodes in another location will not elect a new primary if they
  are unable to see the majority of nodes. However this approach does not
  scale well, particularly with more complex replication setups, e.g.
  where the majority of nodes are located outside of the primary datacentre.
  It also means the <literal>witness</literal> node needs to be managed as an
  extra PostgreSQL instance outside of the main replication cluster, which
  adds administrative and programming complexity.
 </para>
 <para>
  <literal>repmgr4</literal> introduces the concept of <literal>location</literal>:
  each node is associated with an arbitrary location string (default is
  <literal>default</literal>); this is set in <filename>repmgr.conf</filename>, e.g.:
  <programlisting>
    node_id=1
    node_name=node1
    conninfo='host=node1 user=repmgr dbname=repmgr connect_timeout=2'
    data_directory='/var/lib/postgresql/data'
    location='dc1'</programlisting>
 </para>
 <para>
  In a failover situation, &repmgrd; will check if any servers in the
  same location as the current primary node are visible.  If not, &repmgrd;
  will assume a network interruption and not promote any node in any
  other location (it will however enter <link linkend="repmgrd-degraded-monitoring">degraded monitoring</link>
  mode until a primary becomes visible).
 </para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="repmgrd-primary-visibility-consensus" xreflabel="Primary visibility consensus">
  <title>Primary visibility consensus</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>repmgrd</primary>
   <secondary>primary visibility consensus</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>primary_visibility_consensus</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    In more complex replication setups, particularly where replication occurs between
    multiple datacentres, it's possible that some but not all standbys get cut off from the
    primary (but not from the other standbys).
  </para>
  <para>
    In this situation, normally it's not desirable for any of the standbys which have been
    cut off to initiate a failover, as the primary is still functioning and standbys are
    connected. Beginning with <link linkend="release-4.4">&repmgr; 4.4</link>
    it is now possible for the affected standbys to build a consensus about whether
    the primary is still available to some standbys (&quot;primary visibility consensus&quot;).
    This is done by polling each standby (and the witness, if present) for the time it last saw the
    primary; if any have seen the primary very recently, it's reasonable
    to infer that the primary is still available and a failover should not be started.
  </para>

  <para>
    The time the primary was last seen by each node can be checked by executing
    <link linkend="repmgr-service-status"><command>repmgr service status</command></link>
    (&repmgr; 4.2 - 4.4: <link linkend="repmgr-service-status"><command>repmgr daemon status</command></link>)
    which includes this in its output, e.g.:
    <programlisting>$ repmgr -f /etc/repmgr.conf service status
 ID | Name  | Role    | Status    | Upstream | repmgrd | PID   | Paused? | Upstream last seen
----+-------+---------+-----------+----------+---------+-------+---------+--------------------
 1  | node1 | primary | * running |          | running | 27259 | no      | n/a
 2  | node2 | standby |   running | node1    | running | 27272 | no      | 1 second(s) ago
 3  | node3 | standby |   running | node1    | running | 27282 | no      | 0 second(s) ago
 4  | node4 | witness | * running | node1    | running | 27298 | no      | 1 second(s) ago</programlisting>

  </para>

  <para>
    To enable this functionality, in <filename>repmgr.conf</filename> set:
    <programlisting>
      primary_visibility_consensus=true</programlisting>
  </para>
  <note>
    <para>
      <option>primary_visibility_consensus</option> <emphasis>must</emphasis> be set to
      <literal>true</literal> on all nodes for it to be effective.
    </para>
  </note>

  <para>
    The following sample &repmgrd; log output demonstrates the behaviour in a situation
    where one of three standbys is no longer able to connect to the primary, but <emphasis>can</emphasis>
    connect to the two other standbys (&quot;sibling nodes&quot;):
    <programlisting>
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [WARNING] unable to reconnect to node 1 after 3 attempts
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [INFO] 2 active sibling nodes registered
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [INFO] local node's last receive lsn: 0/7006E58
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [INFO] checking state of sibling node "node3" (ID: 3)
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [INFO] node "node3" (ID: 3) reports its upstream is node 1, last seen 1 second(s) ago
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [NOTICE] node 3 last saw primary node 1 second(s) ago, considering primary still visible
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [INFO] last receive LSN for sibling node "node3" (ID: 3) is: 0/7006E58
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [INFO] node "node3" (ID: 3) has same LSN as current candidate "node2" (ID: 2)
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [INFO] checking state of sibling node "node4" (ID: 4)
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [INFO] node "node4" (ID: 4) reports its upstream is node 1, last seen 0 second(s) ago
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [NOTICE] node 4 last saw primary node 0 second(s) ago, considering primary still visible
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [INFO] last receive LSN for sibling node "node4" (ID: 4) is: 0/7006E58
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [INFO] node "node4" (ID: 4) has same LSN as current candidate "node2" (ID: 2)
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [INFO] 2 nodes can see the primary
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [DETAIL] following nodes can see the primary:
     - node "node3" (ID: 3): 1 second(s) ago
     - node "node4" (ID: 4): 0 second(s) ago
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [NOTICE] cancelling failover as some nodes can still see the primary
    [2019-05-17 05:36:12] [NOTICE] election cancelled
    [2019-05-17 05:36:14] [INFO] node "node2" (ID: 2) monitoring upstream node "node1" (ID: 1) in degraded state</programlisting>
    In this situation it will cancel the failover and enter degraded monitoring node,
    waiting for the primary to reappear.
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="repmgrd-standby-disconnection-on-failover" xreflabel="Standby disconnection on failover">
  <title>Standby disconnection on failover</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>repmgrd</primary>
   <secondary>standby disconnection on failover</secondary>
 </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>standby disconnection on failover</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    If <option>standby_disconnect_on_failover</option> is set to <literal>true</literal> in
    <filename>repmgr.conf</filename>, in a failover situation &repmgrd; will forcibly disconnect
    the local node's WAL receiver, and wait for the WAL receiver on all sibling nodes to be
	disconnected, before making a failover decision.
  </para>
  <note>
    <para>
      <option>standby_disconnect_on_failover</option> is available with PostgreSQL 9.5 and later.
      Additionally this requires that the <literal>repmgr</literal> database user is a superuser.
    </para>
  </note>
  <para>
    By doing this, it's possible to ensure that, at the point the failover decision is made, no nodes
    are receiving data from the primary and their LSN location will be static.
  </para>
  <important>
    <para>
      <option>standby_disconnect_on_failover</option> <emphasis>must</emphasis> be set to the same value on
      all nodes.
    </para>
  </important>
  <para>
    Note that when using <option>standby_disconnect_on_failover</option> there will be a delay of 5 seconds
    plus however many seconds it takes to confirm the WAL receiver is disconnected before
    &repmgrd; proceeds with the failover decision.
  </para>
  <para>
	&repmgrd; will wait up to <option>sibling_nodes_disconnect_timeout</option> seconds (default:
	<literal>30</literal>) to confirm that the WAL receiver on all sibling nodes hase been
	disconnected before proceding with the failover operation. If the timeout is reached, the
	failover operation will go ahead anyway.
  </para>
  <para>
    Following the failover operation, no matter what the outcome, each node will reconnect its WAL receiver.
  </para>
  <para>
    If using <option>standby_disconnect_on_failover</option>, we recommend that the
    <option>primary_visibility_consensus</option> option is also used.
  </para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="repmgrd-failover-validation" xreflabel="Failover validation">
  <title>Failover validation</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>repmgrd</primary>
   <secondary>failover validation</secondary>
 </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
    <primary>failover validation</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
    From <link linkend="release-4.3">repmgr 4.3</link>, &repmgr; makes it possible to provide a script
    to &repmgrd; which, in a failover situation,
    will be executed by the promotion candidate (the node which has been selected
    to be the new primary) to confirm whether the node should actually be promoted.
  </para>
  <para>
    To use this, <option>failover_validation_command</option> in <filename>repmgr.conf</filename>
    to a script executable by the <literal>postgres</literal> system user, e.g.:
    <programlisting>
      failover_validation_command=/path/to/script.sh %n</programlisting>
  </para>
  <para>
    The <literal>%n</literal> parameter will be replaced with the node ID when the script is
    executed. A number of other parameters are also available, see section
    &quot;<xref linkend="repmgrd-automatic-failover-configuration-optional"/>&quot; for details.
  </para>
  <para>
    This script must return an exit code of <literal>0</literal> to indicate the node should promote itself.
    Any other value will result in the promotion being aborted and the election rerun.
    There is a pause of <option>election_rerun_interval</option> seconds before the election is rerun.
  </para>
  <para>
    Sample &repmgrd; log file output during which the failover validation
    script rejects the proposed promotion candidate:
    <programlisting>
[2019-03-13 21:01:30] [INFO] visible nodes: 2; total nodes: 2; no nodes have seen the primary within the last 4 seconds
[2019-03-13 21:01:30] [NOTICE] promotion candidate is "node2" (ID: 2)
[2019-03-13 21:01:30] [NOTICE] executing "failover_validation_command"
[2019-03-13 21:01:30] [DETAIL] /usr/local/bin/failover-validation.sh 2
[2019-03-13 21:01:30] [INFO] output returned by failover validation command:
Node ID: 2

[2019-03-13 21:01:30] [NOTICE] failover validation command returned a non-zero value: "1"
[2019-03-13 21:01:30] [NOTICE] promotion candidate election will be rerun
[2019-03-13 21:01:30] [INFO] 1 followers to notify
[2019-03-13 21:01:30] [NOTICE] notifying node "node3" (ID: 3) to rerun promotion candidate selection
INFO:  node 3 received notification to rerun promotion candidate election
[2019-03-13 21:01:30] [NOTICE] rerunning election after 15 seconds ("election_rerun_interval")</programlisting>
  </para>


</sect1>

 <sect1 id="cascading-replication" xreflabel="Cascading replication">
  <title>repmgrd and cascading replication</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>repmgrd</primary>
   <secondary>cascading replication</secondary>
  </indexterm>

 <indexterm>
   <primary>cascading replication</primary>
   <secondary>repmgrd</secondary>
 </indexterm>

 <para>
  Cascading replication - where a standby can connect to an upstream node and not
  the primary server itself - was introduced in PostgreSQL 9.2. &repmgr; and
  &repmgrd; support cascading replication by keeping track of the relationship
  between standby servers - each node record is stored with the node id of its
  upstream ("parent") server (except of course the primary server).
 </para>
 <para>
  In a failover situation where the primary node fails and a top-level standby
  is promoted, a standby connected to another standby will not be affected
  and continue working as normal (even if the upstream standby it's connected
  to becomes the primary node). If however the node's direct upstream fails,
  the &quot;cascaded standby&quot; will attempt to reconnect to that node's parent
  (unless <varname>failover</varname> is set to <literal>manual</literal> in
  <filename>repmgr.conf</filename>).
 </para>

  </sect1>

<sect1 id="repmgrd-primary-child-disconnection" xreflabel="Monitoring standby disconnections on the primary">
  <title>Monitoring standby disconnections on the primary node</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>repmgrd</primary>
   <secondary>standby disconnection</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>repmgrd</primary>
   <secondary>child node disconnection</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <note>
    <para>
      This functionality is available in <link linkend="release-4.4">&repmgr; 4.4</link> and later.
    </para>
  </note>
  <para>
    When running on the primary node, &repmgrd; can
    monitor connections and in particular disconnections by its attached
    child nodes (standbys, and if in use, the witness server), and optionally
    execute a custom command if certain criteria are met (such as the number of
    attached nodes falling to zero following a failover to a new primary); this
    command can be used for example to &quot;fence&quot; the node and ensure it
    is isolated from any applications attempting to access the replication cluster.
  </para>

  <note>
	<para>
	  Currently &repmgrd; can only detect disconnections
	  of streaming replication standbys and cannot determine whether a standby
	  has disconnected and fallen back to archive recovery.
	</para>
	<para>
	  See section <link linkend="repmgrd-primary-child-disconnection-caveats">caveats</link> below.
	</para>
  </note>

  <sect2 id="repmgrd-primary-child-disconnection-monitoring-process">
	<title>Standby disconnections monitoring process and criteria</title>
	<para>
	  &repmgrd; monitors attached child nodes and decides
	  whether to invoke the user-defined command based on the following process
	  and criteria:
    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Every few seconds (defined by the configuration parameter <varname>child_nodes_check_interval</varname>;
          default: <literal>5</literal> seconds, a value of <literal>0</literal> disables this altogether), &repmgrd; queries
          the <literal>pg_stat_replication</literal> system view and compares
          the nodes present there against the list of nodes registered with &repmgr; which
          should be attached to the primary.
        </para>
        <para>
          If a witness server is in use, &repmgrd; connects to it and checks which upstream node
          it is following.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          If a child node (standby) is no longer present in <literal>pg_stat_replication</literal>,
          &repmgrd; notes the time it detected the node's absence, and additionally generates a
          <literal>child_node_disconnect</literal> event.
        </para>
        <para>
          If a witness server is in use, and it is no longer following the primary, or not
          reachable at all, &repmgrd; notes the time it detected the node's absence, and additionally generates a
          <literal>child_node_disconnect</literal> event.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          If a child node (standby) which was absent from <literal>pg_stat_replication</literal> reappears,
          &repmgrd; clears the time it detected the node's absence, and additionally generates a
          <literal>child_node_reconnect</literal> event.
        </para>
        <para>
          If a witness server is in use, which was previously not reachable or not following the
          primary node, has become reachable and is following the primary node,  &repmgrd; clears the
          time it detected the node's absence, and additionally generates a
          <literal>child_node_reconnect</literal> event.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          If an entirely new child node (standby or witness) is detected, &repmgrd; adds it to its internal list
          and additionally generates a <literal>child_node_new_connect</literal> event.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          If the <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname> parameter is set in
          <filename>repmgr.conf</filename>, &repmgrd; will then loop through all child nodes.
          If it determines that insufficient child nodes are connected, and a
          minimum of <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_timeout</varname> seconds (default: <literal>30</literal>)
          has elapsed since  the last node became disconnected, &repmgrd; will then execute the
          <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname> script.
        </para>
        <para>
          By default, the <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname> will only be executed
          if all child nodes are disconnected. If <varname>child_nodes_connected_min_count</varname>
          is set, the <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname> script will be triggered
          if the number of connected child nodes falls below the specified value (e.g.
          if set to <literal>2</literal>, the script will be triggered if only one child node
          is connected). Alternatively, if <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_min_count</varname>
          and more than that number of child nodes disconnects, the script will be triggered.
        </para>
        <note>
          <para>
            By default, a witness node, if in use, will <emphasis>not</emphasis> be counted as a
            child node for the purposes of determining whether to execute
            <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname>.
          </para>
          <para>
            To enable the witness node to be counted as a child node, set
            <varname>child_nodes_connected_include_witness</varname> in <filename>repmgr.conf</filename>
            to <literal>true</literal>
            (and <link linkend="repmgrd-reloading-configuration">reload the configuration</link> if &repmgrd;
            is running).
          </para>
        </note>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Note that child nodes which are not attached when &repmgrd;
          starts will <emphasis>not</emphasis> be considered as missing, as &repmgrd;
          cannot know why they are not attached.
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
	</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="repmgrd-primary-child-disconnection-example">
	<title>Standby disconnections monitoring process example</title>
	<para>
	  This example shows typical &repmgrd; log output from a three-node cluster
	  (primary and two child nodes), with <varname>child_nodes_connected_min_count</varname>
	  set to <literal>2</literal>.
	</para>
	<para>
	  &repmgrd; on the primary has started up, while two child
	  nodes are being provisioned:
	  <programlisting>
[2019-04-24 15:25:33] [INFO] monitoring primary node "node1" (ID: 1) in normal state
[2019-04-24 15:25:35] [NOTICE] new node "node2" (ID: 2) has connected
[2019-04-24 15:25:35] [NOTICE] 1 (of 1) child nodes are connected, but at least 2 child nodes required
[2019-04-24 15:25:35] [INFO] no child nodes have detached since repmgrd startup
(...)
[2019-04-24 15:25:44] [NOTICE] new node "node3" (ID: 3) has connected
[2019-04-24 15:25:46] [INFO] monitoring primary node "node1" (ID: 1) in normal state
(...)</programlisting>
	</para>
	<para>
	  One of the child nodes has disconnected; &repmgrd;
	  is now waiting <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_timeout</varname> seconds
	  before executing <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname>:
	  <programlisting>
[2019-04-24 15:28:11] [INFO] monitoring primary node "node1" (ID: 1) in normal state
[2019-04-24 15:28:17] [INFO] monitoring primary node "node1" (ID: 1) in normal state
[2019-04-24 15:28:19] [NOTICE] node "node3" (ID: 3) has disconnected
[2019-04-24 15:28:19] [NOTICE] 1 (of 2) child nodes are connected, but at least 2 child nodes required
[2019-04-24 15:28:19] [INFO] most recently detached child node was 3 (ca. 0 seconds ago), not triggering "child_nodes_disconnect_command"
[2019-04-24 15:28:19] [DETAIL] "child_nodes_disconnect_timeout" set To 30 seconds
(...)</programlisting>
	</para>
	<para>
	  <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname> is executed once:
	  <programlisting>
[2019-04-24 15:28:49] [INFO] most recently detached child node was 3 (ca. 30 seconds ago), triggering "child_nodes_disconnect_command"
[2019-04-24 15:28:49] [INFO] "child_nodes_disconnect_command" is:
	"/usr/bin/fence-all-the-things.sh"
[2019-04-24 15:28:51] [NOTICE] 1 (of 2) child nodes are connected, but at least 2 child nodes required
[2019-04-24 15:28:51] [INFO] "child_nodes_disconnect_command" was previously executed, taking no action</programlisting>
	</para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="repmgrd-primary-child-disconnection-caveats">
	<title>Standby disconnections monitoring caveats</title>
	<para>
	  The follwing caveats should be considered if you are intending to use this functionality.
	</para>
	<para>
	  <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
		<listitem>
          <para>
			If a child node is configured to use archive recovery, it's possible that
			the child node will disconnect from the primary node and fall back to
			archive recovery. In this case &repmgrd;
			will nevertheless register a node disconnection.
		  </para>
		</listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
			&repmgr; relies on <varname>application_name</varname> in the child node's
			<varname>primary_conninfo</varname> string to be the same as the node name
			defined in the node's <filename>repmgr.conf</filename> file. Furthermore,
			this <varname>application_name</varname> must be unique across the replication
			cluster.
          </para>
		  <para>
			If a custom <varname>application_name</varname> is used, or the
			<varname>application_name</varname> is not unique across the replication
			cluster, &repmgr; will not be able to reliably monitor child node connections.
		  </para>
        </listitem>

	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
  </sect2>


  <sect2 id="repmgrd-primary-child-disconnection-configuration">
	<title>Standby disconnections monitoring process configuration</title>
	<para>
	  The following parameters, set in <filename>repmgr.conf</filename>,
	  control how child node disconnection monitoring operates.
	</para>
	<variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>child_nodes_check_interval</varname></term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
		    <primary>child_nodes_check_interval</primary>
		    <secondary>child node disconnection monitoring</secondary>
		  </indexterm>

		  <para>
			Interval (in seconds) after which &repmgrd; queries the
			<literal>pg_stat_replication</literal> system view and compares the nodes present
			there against the list of nodes registered with repmgr which should be attached to the primary.
		  </para>
		  <para>
			Default is <literal>5</literal> seconds, a value of <literal>0</literal> disables this check
			altogether.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname></term>

        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
		    <primary>child_nodes_disconnect_command</primary>
		    <secondary>child node disconnection monitoring</secondary>
		  </indexterm>

		  <para>
			User-definable script to be executed when &repmgrd;
			determines that an insufficient number of child nodes are connected. By default
			the script is executed when no child nodes are executed, but the execution
			threshold can be modified by setting one of <varname>child_nodes_connected_min_count</varname>
			or<varname>child_nodes_disconnect_min_count</varname> (see below).
		  </para>
		  <para>
			The <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname> script can be
			any user-defined script or program. It <emphasis>must</emphasis> be able
			to be executed by the system user under which the PostgreSQL server itself
			runs (usually <literal>postgres</literal>).
		  </para>
		  <note>
			<para>
			  If <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname> is not set, no action
			  will be taken.
			</para>
		  </note>
		  <para>
			If specified, the following format placeholder will be substituted when
			executing <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname>:
		  </para>

		   <variablelist>
			 <varlistentry>
			   <term><option>%p</option></term>
			   <listitem>
				 <para>
				   ID of the node executing the <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname> script.
				 </para>
			   </listitem>
			 </varlistentry>
		   </variablelist>

		  <para>
			The <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname> script will only be executed once
			while the criteria for its execution are met. If the criteria for its execution are no longer
			met (i.e. some child nodes have reconnected), it will be executed again if
			the criteria for its execution are met again.
          </para>
          <para>
			The <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname> script will not be executed if
			&repmgrd; is <link linkend="repmgrd-pausing">paused</link>.
          </para>

		</listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>child_nodes_disconnect_timeout</varname></term>

        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
		    <primary>child_nodes_disconnect_timeout</primary>
		    <secondary>child node disconnection monitoring</secondary>
		  </indexterm>

		  <para>
			If &repmgrd; determines that an insufficient number of
			child nodes are connected, it will wait for the specified number of seconds
			to execute the <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname>.
		  </para>
		  <para>
			Default: <literal>30</literal> seconds.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	  </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>child_nodes_connected_min_count</varname></term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
		    <primary>child_nodes_connected_min_count</primary>
		    <secondary>child node disconnection monitoring</secondary>
		  </indexterm>

		  <para>
			If the number of child nodes connected falls below the number specified in
			this parameter, the <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname> script
			will be executed.
		  </para>
		  <para>
			For example, if <varname>child_nodes_connected_min_count</varname> is set
			to <literal>2</literal>, the <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname>
			script will be executed if one or no child nodes are connected.
		  </para>
		  <para>
			Note that <varname>child_nodes_connected_min_count</varname> overrides any value
			set in <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_min_count</varname>.
		  </para>
		  <para>
			If neither of <varname>child_nodes_connected_min_count</varname> or
			<varname>child_nodes_disconnect_min_count</varname> are set,
			the <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname> script
			will be executed when no child nodes are connected.
		  </para>
          <para>
            A witness node, if in use, will not be counted as a child node unless
            <varname>child_nodes_connected_include_witness</varname> is set to <literal>true</literal>.
          </para>
		</listitem>
	  </varlistentry>


	  <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>child_nodes_disconnect_min_count</varname></term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
		    <primary>child_nodes_disconnect_min_count</primary>
		    <secondary>child node disconnection monitoring</secondary>
		  </indexterm>

		  <para>
			If the number of disconnected child nodes exceeds the number specified in
			this parameter, the <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname> script
			will be executed.
		  </para>

		  <para>
			For example, if <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_min_count</varname> is set
			to <literal>2</literal>, the <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname>
			script will be executed if more than two child nodes are disconnected.
		  </para>

		  <para>
			Note that any value set in <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_min_count</varname>
			will be overriden by <varname>child_nodes_connected_min_count</varname>.
		  </para>
		  <para>
			If neither of <varname>child_nodes_connected_min_count</varname> or
			<varname>child_nodes_disconnect_min_count</varname> are set,
			the <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname> script
			will be executed when no child nodes are connected.
		  </para>

          <para>
            A witness node, if in use, will not be counted as a child node unless
            <varname>child_nodes_connected_include_witness</varname> is set to <literal>true</literal>.
          </para>

		</listitem>
	  </varlistentry>


	  <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>child_nodes_connected_include_witness</varname></term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
		    <primary>child_nodes_connected_include_witness</primary>
		    <secondary>child node disconnection monitoring</secondary>
		  </indexterm>

		  <para>
            Whether to count the witness node (if in use) as a child node when
            determining whether to execute <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname>.
          </para>
          <para>
            Default to <literal>false</literal>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

	</variablelist>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="repmgrd-primary-child-disconnection-events">
	<title>Standby disconnections monitoring process event notifications</title>
	<para>
	  The following <link linkend="event-notifications">event notifications</link> may be generated:
	</para>
	<variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>child_node_disconnect</varname></term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
		    <primary>child_node_disconnect</primary>
		    <secondary>event notification</secondary>
		  </indexterm>

          <para>
			This event is generated after &repmgrd;
			detects that a child node is no longer streaming from the primary node.
          </para>
		  <para>
			Example:
			<programlisting>
$ repmgr cluster event --event=child_node_disconnect
 Node ID | Name  | Event                 | OK | Timestamp           | Details
---------+-------+-----------------------+----+---------------------+--------------------------------------------
 1       | node1 | child_node_disconnect | t  | 2019-04-24 12:41:36 | node "node3" (ID: 3) has disconnected</programlisting>
		  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>child_node_reconnect</varname></term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
		    <primary>child_node_reconnect</primary>
		    <secondary>event notification</secondary>
		  </indexterm>

          <para>
			This event is generated after &repmgrd;
			detects that a child node has resumed streaming from the primary node.
          </para>
		  <para>
			Example:
			<programlisting>
$ repmgr cluster event --event=child_node_reconnect
 Node ID | Name  | Event                | OK | Timestamp           | Details
---------+-------+----------------------+----+---------------------+------------------------------------------------------------
 1       | node1 | child_node_reconnect | t  | 2019-04-24 12:42:19 | node "node3" (ID: 3) has reconnected after 42 seconds</programlisting>
		  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>child_node_new_connect</varname></term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
		    <primary>child_node_new_connect</primary>
		    <secondary>event notification</secondary>
		  </indexterm>

          <para>
			This event is generated after &repmgrd;
			detects that a new child node has been registered with &repmgr; and has
			connected to the primary.
          </para>
		  <para>
			Example:
			<programlisting>
$ repmgr cluster event --event=child_node_new_connect
 Node ID | Name  | Event                  | OK | Timestamp           | Details
---------+-------+------------------------+----+---------------------+---------------------------------------------
 1       | node1 | child_node_new_connect | t  | 2019-04-24 12:41:30 | new node "node3" (ID: 3) has connected</programlisting>
		  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname></term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
		    <primary>child_nodes_disconnect_command</primary>
		    <secondary>event notification</secondary>
		  </indexterm>

          <para>
			This event is generated after &repmgrd; detects
			that sufficient child nodes have been disconnected for a sufficient amount
			of time to trigger execution of the <varname>child_nodes_disconnect_command</varname>.
          </para>
		  <para>
			Example:
			<programlisting>
$ repmgr cluster event --event=child_nodes_disconnect_command
 Node ID | Name  | Event                          | OK | Timestamp           | Details
---------+-------+--------------------------------+----+---------------------+--------------------------------------------------------
 1       | node1 | child_nodes_disconnect_command | t  | 2019-04-24 13:08:17 | "child_nodes_disconnect_command" successfully executed</programlisting>
		  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

	</variablelist>

  </sect2>


</sect1>


</chapter>
