<refentry id="repmgr-standby-switchover">
  <indexterm>
    <primary>repmgr standby switchover</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>repmgr standby switchover</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>repmgr standby switchover</refname>
    <refpurpose>promote a standby to primary and demote the existing primary to a standby</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>


  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>

    <para>
      Promotes a standby to primary and demotes the existing primary to a standby.
      This command must be run on the standby to be promoted, and requires a
      passwordless SSH connection to the current primary.
    </para>
    <para>
      If other nodes are connected to the demotion candidate, &repmgr; can instruct
      these to follow the new primary if the option <literal>--siblings-follow</literal>
      is specified. This requires a passwordless SSH connection between the promotion
      candidate (new primary) and the nodes attached to the demotion candidate
      (existing primary). Note that a witness server, if in use, is also
	  counted as a &quot;sibling node&quot; as it needs to be instructed to
	  synchronise its metadata with the new primary.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Performing a switchover is a non-trivial operation. In particular it
        relies on the current primary being able to shut down cleanly and quickly.
        &repmgr; will attempt to check for potential issues but cannot guarantee
        a successful switchover.
      </para>
      <para>
        &repmgr; will refuse to perform the switchover if an exclusive backup is running on
        the current primary, or if WAL replay is paused on the standby.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      For more details on performing a switchover, including preparation and configuration,
      see section <xref linkend="performing-switchover"/>.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        From <link linkend="release-4.2">repmgr 4.2</link>, &repmgr; will instruct any running
        &repmgrd; instances to pause operations while the switchover
        is being carried out, to prevent &repmgrd; from
        unintentionally promoting a node. For more details, see <xref linkend="repmgrd-pausing"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        Users of &repmgr; versions prior to 4.2 should ensure that &repmgrd;
        is not running on any nodes while a switchover is being executed.
      </para>
    </note>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>User permission requirements</title>
    <para><emphasis>CHECKPOINT</emphasis></para>
    <para>
      &repmgr; executes <command>CHECKPOINT</command> on the demotion candidate as part of the shutdown
      process to ensure it shuts down as smoothly as possible.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note that <command>CHECKPOINT</command> requires database superuser permissions to execute.
      If the <literal>repmgr</literal> user is not a superuser, the name of a superuser should be
      provided with the <option>-S</option>/<option>--superuser</option>.
    </para>
    <para>
      If &repmgr; is unable to execute the <command>CHECKPOINT</command> command, the switchover
      can still be carried out, albeit at a greater risk that the demotion candidate may not
      be able to shut down as smoothly as might otherwise have been the case.
    </para>
    <para><emphasis>pg_promote() (PostgreSQL 12 and later)</emphasis></para>
    <para>
      From PostgreSQL 12, &repmgr; defaults to using the built-in <command>pg_promote()</command> function to
      promote a standby to primary.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note that execution of <function>pg_promote()</function> is restricted to superusers or to
      any user who has been granted execution permission for this function. If the &repmgr; user
      is not permitted to execute <function>pg_promote()</function>, &repmgr; will fall back to using
      &quot;<command>pg_ctl promote</command>&quot;. For more details see
      <link linkend="repmgr-standby-promote">repmgr standby promote</link>.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>

    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>--always-promote</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Promote standby to primary, even if it is behind or has diverged
            from the original primary. The original primary will be shut down in any case,
            and will need to be manually reintegrated into the replication cluster.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>--dry-run</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Check prerequisites but don't actually execute a switchover.
          </para>
          <important>
            <para>
              Success of <option>--dry-run</option> does not imply the switchover will
              complete successfully, only that
              the prerequisites for performing the operation are met.
            </para>
          </important>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>-F</option></term>
        <term><option>--force</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Ignore warnings and continue anyway.
          </para>
          <para>
            Specifically, if a problem is encountered when shutting down the current primary,
            using <option>-F/--force</option> will cause &repmgr; to continue by promoting
            the standby to be the new primary, and if <option>--siblings-follow</option> is
            specified, attach any other standbys to the new primary.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>--force-rewind[=/path/to/pg_rewind]</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Use <application>pg_rewind</application> to reintegrate the old primary if necessary
            (and the prerequisites for using <application>pg_rewind</application> are met).
            If using PostgreSQL 9.4, and the <application>pg_rewind</application>
            binary is not installed in the PostgreSQL <filename>bin</filename> directory,
            provide its full path. For more details see also <xref linkend="switchover-pg-rewind"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>-R</option></term>
        <term><option>--remote-user</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            System username for remote SSH operations (defaults to local system user).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>--repmgrd-no-pause</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Don't pause &repmgrd; while executing a switchover.
          </para>
          <para>
            This option should not be used unless you take steps by other means
            to ensure &repmgrd; is paused or not
            running on all nodes.
          </para>
		  <para>
            This option cannot be used together with <option>--repmgrd-force-unpause</option>.
          </para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

	  <varlistentry>
        <term><option>--repmgrd-force-unpause</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Always unpause all &repmgrd; instances after executing a switchover. This will ensure that
			any &repmgrd; instances which were paused before the switchover will be
			unpaused.
          </para>
          <para>
            This option cannot be used together with <option>--repmgrd-no-pause</option>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>


     <varlistentry>

        <term><option>--siblings-follow</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Have nodes attached to the old primary follow the new primary.
          </para>
          <para>
            This will also ensure that a witness node, if in use, is updated
            with the new primary's data.
          </para>
          <note>
            <para>
              In a future &repmgr; release, <option>--siblings-follow</option> will be applied
              by default.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry>
        <term><option>-S</option>/<option>--superuser</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Use the named superuser instead of the normal &repmgr; user to perform
            actions requiring superuser permissions.
          </para>
        </listitem>
     </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Configuration file settings</title>

    <para>
     The following parameters in <filename>repmgr.conf</filename> are relevant to the
     switchover operation:
    </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>replication_lag_critical</option></term>
        <listitem>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>replication_lag_critical</primary>
            <secondary>with &quot;repmgr standby switchover&quot;</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <para>
            If replication lag (in seconds) on the standby exceeds this value, the
            switchover will be aborted (unless the <literal>-F/--force</literal> option
            is provided)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>

        <term><option>shutdown_check_timeout</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>shutdown_check_timeout</primary>
            <secondary>with &quot;repmgr standby switchover&quot;</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <para>
            The maximum number of seconds to wait for the
            demotion candidate (current primary) to shut down, before aborting the switchover.
          </para>
          <para>
            Note that this parameter is set on the node where <command>repmgr standby switchover</command>
            is executed (promotion candidate); setting it on the demotion candidate (former primary) will
            have no effect.
          </para>
         <note>
           <para>
             In versions prior to <link linkend="release-4.2">&repmgr; 4.2</link>, <command>repmgr standby switchover</command> would
             use the values defined in <literal>reconnect_attempts</literal> and <literal>reconnect_interval</literal>
             to determine the timeout for demotion candidate shutdown.
           </para>
         </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>wal_receive_check_timeout</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>wal_receive_check_timeout</primary>
          <secondary>with &quot;repmgr standby switchover&quot;</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <para>
            After the primary has shut down, the maximum number of seconds to wait for the
            walreceiver on the standby to flush WAL to disk before comparing WAL receive location
            with the primary's shut down location.
         </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>


      <varlistentry>

        <term><option>standby_reconnect_timeout</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>standby_reconnect_timeout</primary>
            <secondary>with &quot;repmgr standby switchover&quot;</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <para>
            The maximum number of seconds to attempt to wait for the demotion candidate (former primary)
            to reconnect to the promoted primary (default: 60 seconds)
          </para>
          <para>
            Note that this parameter is set on the node where <command>repmgr standby switchover</command>
            is executed (promotion candidate); setting it on the demotion candidate (former primary) will
            have no effect.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>

        <term><option>node_rejoin_timeout</option></term>
        <listitem>

          <indexterm>
            <primary>node_rejoin_timeout</primary>
            <secondary>with &quot;repmgr standby switchover&quot;</secondary>
          </indexterm>

          <para>
            maximum number of seconds to attempt to wait for the demotion candidate (former primary)
            to reconnect to the promoted primary (default: 60 seconds)
          </para>
          <para>
            Note that this parameter is set on the the demotion candidate (former primary);
            setting it on the node where <command>repmgr standby switchover</command> is
            executed will have no effect.
          </para>
          <para>
            However, this value <emphasis>must</emphasis> be less than <option>standby_reconnect_timeout</option> on the
            promotion candidate (the node where <command>repmgr standby switchover</command> is executed).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

  </refsect1>


  <refsect1>
    <title>Execution</title>

    <para>
      Execute with the <literal>--dry-run</literal> option to test the switchover as far as
      possible without actually changing the status of either node.
    </para>

    <para>
      External database connections, e.g. from an application, should not be permitted while
      the switchover is taking place. In particular, active transactions on the primary
      can potentially disrupt the shutdown process.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="repmgr-standby-switchover-events">
    <title>Event notifications</title>
    <para>
      <literal>standby_switchover</literal> and <literal>standby_promote</literal>
      <link linkend="event-notifications">event notifications</link> will be generated for the new primary,
      and a <literal>node_rejoin</literal> event notification for the former primary (new standby).
    </para>
    <para>
      If using an event notification script, <literal>standby_switchover</literal>
      will populate the placeholder parameter <literal>%p</literal> with the node ID of
      the former primary.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Exit codes</title>
    <para>
      One of the following exit codes will be emitted by <command>repmgr standby switchover</command>:
    </para>
    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>SUCCESS (0)</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The switchover completed successfully; or if <option>--dry-run</option> was provided,
            no issues were detected which would prevent the switchover operation.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>ERR_SWITCHOVER_FAIL (18)</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The switchover could not be executed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>ERR_SWITCHOVER_INCOMPLETE (22)</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The switchover was executed but a problem was encountered.
            Typically this means the former primary could not be reattached
            as a standby. Check preceding log messages for more information.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

   </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>See also</title>
    <para>
      <xref linkend="repmgr-standby-follow"/>, <xref linkend="repmgr-node-rejoin"/>
    </para>
    <para>
      For more details on performing a switchover operation, see the section <xref linkend="performing-switchover"/>.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

</refentry>
